Inventory of the Dorsey-Coupland Papers 1840-1876, 1843-1865
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Letters, 1840-1866, n.d., 174 items. (Box-folder 1:1-4)
  - Jane [S. Dupuy], Prince Edward [County], to her sister [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 24 Feb[ruary] 1864., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Apologizes for not writing sooner but reminds her that her [JSD] vision is very bad; is thankful she is staying with the General [Cocke]; feels anger over the boarding situation, in that there is no family willing to take on an extra person without fee, and the Confederate money is so worthless that many families do not wish to bother; seeks a place for her "poor suffering child who is not strong enough to bear this constant shifting and change of place" but has yet to be successful; regrets Sue's decision to submit to medical treatment for she is more of an invalid than before; notwithstanding Dr. Henly's "kindest feeling and the purest motives"; sends word that Charlie believes that Sherman will march on the South, attacking Mobile, Selma, and Montgomery simultaneously; hopes Mary and John [Marshall] will not remain in Mobile long; informs her that her headaches are gone, but now she cannot see well enough to do even her own mending; mentions a letter her son received from John [R. Coupland] detailing the provisions and supplies he was able to bring with his family out of Williamsburg; shares news of family and friends.
  - Carter [Coupland], on board Steamer Reindeer, Selma, [Alabama], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 5 M[ar]ch 1864., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Has been doing the work of two men but will not complain because these are war times; has been mostly ferrying troops for the last three weeks; mentions that John and Mollie [Marshall] had made the trip up with him on their way to Virginia; had had about 400 passengers on that trip, mostly women and children; feels that Mobile is one of the safest places in the Confederacy at this time; will dispose of the sugar he owns on his next trip to Mobile if he can double his money; feels sugar is a luxury and does not think it wrong to speculate in it.
  - John [R. Coupland], Ashland, [Virginia], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 3 Ap[ril] 1864., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Mentions that Sue and the youngest two children have been away in King & Queen County for two weeks visiting her relatives and seeking to fill their larder; provisions are hard to come by and quite expensive; thanks her profusely for the clothes she made and sent for him and his family but tells her not to tax her eyes any more; had hoped to see her this summer but fears by then they will be behind enemy lines once more; does not know where he can go if General Lee falls back to Richmond; mentions that Sue saw John Marshall, Willie Dupuy, and Tom Ruffin a few days previously.
  - Eugene Desdunes, [Richmond, Virginia], to Mattie Pierce, Richmond, Virginia, 4 June 1864., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Asks her to accept the gift of cherries enclosed and to let him know whether they reached her in good order as he neglected to pay the insurance on them.
  - E.C. B[oudinot], [Richmond, Virginia], to Mattie Pierce, Richmond, Virginia, 8 June 1864., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Informs her that she did not regret her absence last evening more than he did; came to see her last evening before he went home; hopes to see her today.
  - [E.C.] B[oudinot], [Richmond, Virginia], to Mattie Peirce [sic], Richmond, Virginia, 10 June 1864., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Has taken the liberty of promising that she will accompany Miss Jane, Miss Lottie, and the subscriber to Miss Wallace's this evening. Enclosure: memorandum of the addresses of E.C. Boudinot.
  - E.[C. Boudinot], [Richmond, Virginia], to Mattie Peirce [sic], Richmond, Virginia, 12 June 1864., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Hopes that his "promptness will make amends for forgetfulness" in enclosing his likeness; wanted to improve the portrait "by a few master touches with this pen but was 'afraid'." Enclosure: Portrait in watercolor of E.C. Boudinot.
  - Daniel Wheeler, Mobile, [Alabama] to Juliana Dorsey, n.p., 13 June 1864., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Has some more money from Messrs. Booth & Foster in virtue of her "Big Risk" and wonders how to send it to her; hopes she is well; informs her that Mr. and Mrs. Burgith[?] are at the point in the hopes of it benefiting Sarah, who is still distressed over the loss of her child.
  - [E.] C. [Boudinot], Meridian, Miss., to Mattie Pierce, n.p., 20 June 1864., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Has arrived in Meridian ahead of the rest of his party, who will overtake him today; met an old acquaintance from Fayetteville on the journey down that he addressed as Miss Marshall but who has since married a Mr. Boomer; informs her that every day at ten minutes to three p.m. and again about 6 p.m. his thoughts return to her and Richmond; has found a sure way for her to write to him care of Mr. Charles Watson with Major Young.
  - Edmund Ruffin, near Mattoax P.O., Amelia, Virginia, to "Sister" [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 20 June 1864., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Thanks her for her letter of consolation on the death of his son [Julian?]; mourns his son's death but is thankful that the death blow was instantaneous and that he died serving his country; shares information regarding his family and the escapes they had to make from the Yankee army; informs her that the total of the land that his sons own is four plantations laid to waste "by the depredations... of the enemy, and which must remain waste and unproductive as long as the war lasts."
  - Carter [Coupland], Montgomery, [Alabama], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 12 July [18]64., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Informs her that "Everything at present looks gloomy; but we must hope for the best"; the Reindeer has laid up and so he has made some trips on the Senator; is in Montgomery to settle the business; hopes to be able to come see her as soon as he gets through to Mobile; informs her that the "Board" has given him a full discharge.
  - Carter [Coupland], Selma, [Alabama] to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 9 Aug[ust 18]64., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Believes it will be several weeks before the Yankees make an attack by land in Mississippi; had business in Selma and wanted to settle it, especially since they were putting everyone in trenches in Mobile; worries that it looks "as if I was not willing to do what I could towards defending the old town, so... I must return to strife and excitement"; assures her that if his services are not needed he will come to see her soon.
  - [E.]C. [Boudinot], Washington, Arkansas, to [Mattie Pierce], n.p., 10 August 1864., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Does not believe that she deserves another letter as she will not write to him; informs her that he must go to work again after a long break; remembers their walks together in Richmond and pretends that he is with her now; asks if she goes to see the Cloftons now and reminds her they never paid that visit to the Jacksons.
  - J[uliana] Dorsey, Greensboro, to John [R. Coupland], n.p., 16 Aug[ust 18]64., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Did not receive his letter for some time after he sent it, but would rather get his letters late than not at all; is sorry to hear that his family is complaining; gives suggestions for the recovery of his health; will get Carter to attempt again to send the 100 lbs. of bacon she purchased a while ago; informs him that though the Examining Board gave Carter a full discharge, he may still volunteer; asks whether his family has a cow; gives the prices of provisions in Montgomery, which are much lower than in Richmond; shares news of family and friends; mentions the difficulty faced by Brother Edmund and his son Edmund in obtaining food; informs him that in the Examinerof 26 May there was a nice piece on the death of J.E.B. Stuart; asks if he can get it for her from the office; sends him some verses that she wrote when he was attempting to rescue his family from Williamsburg; tells him Carter will send notice when he is ready to send the meat, if he can at all.
  - Lou [?], Richmond, [Virginia] to [?], 23 Aug[us]t [18]64., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Reminisces about their time spent together and is thankful he is loved by her; has been refreshed by the rain that has fallen to relieve the heat of the summer; gives news of many common friends that are now refugees in Richmond with him.
  - Carter [Coupland], on board Steamer Dixie, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 27 Aug[ust 18]64., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Guesses that his last letter to her was never received by her; has collected $160 from Mr. Wheeler; was forced to remain in Mobile and is now without funds; is surviving without shoes and nearly without clothing; informs her that the sugar she owns will pay the amount of money invested; believes that if he were to invest in a gold mine it would be worthless within a short time; was not able to get her sugar out of Mobile, but left it with a good family with instructions to sell it; is disappointed by the quality of the sugar; would love to be able to help out his Brother [John] but has not the funds at this time; informs him that the government is not paying anything, the quartermasters have had no money for six or seven months, and therefore the steamers have not been receiving any pay for their services.
  - Juliana [Coupland], Ashland, [Virginia], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 1 September 1864., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Has not heard from her in a while but guesses it is due to the lack of regularity in the mails; informs her that Father [John R. Coupland] has gone to Huguenot Springs to see Dr. Walker; he tells her that the food there is too good for a poor clerk; mentions the love felt by the children for their father; Little Carter has been sick but is recovering now; loves their house in Ashland; is excited about going to school in Richmond.
  - Carter [Coupland], on board Steamer Dixie, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 9 Sept[ember 18]64., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Thanks her for sending the letter from Aunt Jane as he has not heard from them in quite a while; shares news from a letter he received from Brother [John], informing him that Harriet is staying with them, as is Miss Mattie, who is quite ill, that his health is not good owing to his old complaint of the liver, and that he now weighs 117 lbs.; thanks her for her offer of mending his clothes and will send them as soon as possible; informs her that good brown sugar is selling for $4 a pound in Selma and assures her that she can do better in Greensboro; mentions the fact that the Government has not paid anyone for eight months.
  - Ro[bert] Saunders, Pittsylvania C[ourt] House, to John R. Coupland, n.p., 12 Sept[ember] 1864., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Asks him to give the letter enclosed to Mr. Marye; inquires about John Henley [sic] and asks if he will tell him [JH] to write to him [RS]; sends his regards to his wife and children; describes his work.
  - [Juliana Dorsey], Greensboro, to John [R. Coupland], n.p., 23 Sept[embe]r [18]64., 4 pages. AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Has heard from Harriet Cary that he is back from his trip but would like to know if it benefited him; is uneasy about his state of health; is distressed that he weighs only 117 lbs; wishes he could have gone to Coyner's Springs instead and drunk their sulfur water to help heal him; asks after the health of his family; has just finished a pair of warm gloves for him, along with 5 pairs of socks for him and 6 pairs for little Johnie [sic], but cannot find anyone to carry them up for her; gives prices of provisions; shares news of family and friends.
  - Carter [Coupland], on board Steamer Dixie, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 28 Sept[ember] 1864., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Received her letter that enclosed one from Harriet; is very glad she is now well; mentions that he will be able to come see her as soon as Capt. Locklin returns from seeing his sick family, which should be after two or three weeks; will bring the clothes that need repairing when he comes.
  - Ro[bert] Saunders, at Pittsylvania C[ourt] House, to John R. Coupland, n.p., 28 Sept[ember] 1864., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Was extremely glad to receive a letter from him as it cheered him immensely; would find the trials easier to bear if he had one of his best friends with him; has been joined by his family and is enjoying perfect health; thanks him for helping him out in the matter of the money lent to Mr. Marye, but is upset that Mr. Marye felt the need to pay interest on the loan as he was not out to make an investment when he lent the money to him; informs him that his son Bob was home on a furlough to recover from illness but has since returned to the army as a clerk; hopes that his health returns soon; had heard with concern of the death of Mattie Pierce.
  - Carter Coupland, Demopolis, [Alabama], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 13 Oct[ober] 1864., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Has been ordered from Selma to Demopolis and made one trip up the Bigbee River; was glad to have Capt. Locklin back in command after visiting his family as he [CC] is unfamiliar with these rivers; hopes to see her soon, but will find it difficult because they are frequently ordered to another city, and will not easily find the boat again upon his return.
  - Carter Coupland, on board the Steamer Dixie, Demopolis, [Alabama], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 18 Oct[ober] 1864., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Cannot move up the Bigbee River as it is too low; expects to move down the river to pick up corn to take to Selma; hopes to get away tomorrow and will be in Selma within four or five days; wonders if "this cruel war [will] never end"; longs to see her.
  - Lou M. L[?], Richmond, [Virginia], to [?], 3 Nov[ember 18]64., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Warns her not to expect him till she tells him whether she is leaving soon; sends his love and affection to her; asks if she can procure two rooms for him, as his doctor highly recommends the change; shares much news of family and friends.
  - Carter [Coupland], Selma, [Alabama], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 1 April 1865., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Arrived in Selma the day before and will leave that evening on the steamer Cherokee for Montgomery; the Dixie sunk and burnt on the 24th of March but the crew and passengers are all safe; informs her of the great excitement there over the Yankee raids.
  - J[uliana] D[orsey], at Cousin George's Canebrake, to John [R. Coupland], n.p., 9 Sept[embe]r [18]65., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Is greatly worried about him and has no idea where he is; could not guess where he went after the evacuation of Richmond; hopes that he had gone to her place and used anything there which would benefit him, as she does not envision having money enough to go to Virginia for a long time yet; informs him that "the Yankees hold all offices and impose such insults and oppressive measures on the citizens that no one seems to feel secure, or ventures to make any but a temporary arrangement"; shares news of family and friends; sends word of Carter and his escape from the Dixie as she burned and sank.
  - J[ohn] R. Coupland, Ashland, Hanover County, Virginia, to John [?], 20 Sept[ember] 1865., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Asks if he could secure a place for his [JRC] son in a business house in his [J] city, as business is hard to come by in his [JRC] part of the country; asks after Mother [Juliana Dorsey] and Brother [Carter] as he has not heard from him since the surrender; will not go down to Mother's farm before November.
  - J[ohn] R. Coupland, Williamsburg, [Virginia], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 20 Dec[embe]r 1865., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Has not written to her lately because he has been expecting to move out to the farm to live; is glad to hear of Brother's [Carter] recovery; has yet to find a job to support himself and his family; wants to move out to the farm so that he can support his family off the land and devote himself to his children's education; explains that Mr. Darlington did not owe him $2000 as she had thought, but only $700, which is almost paid off; informs her that the $700 barely bought clothing and supplies of food; wonders "What is to become of us all"; is staying at Dr.'s with Johnny while Sue, the girls, and Little Carter are at Mrs. Henley's; shares news of friends and family.
  - J[uliana] Dorsey, Mobile, [Alabama], to [John R. Coupland], n.p., 29 May 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Explains that her school is so small because she started in February, when all the scholars were at other schools, and also that the smallpox was in every house in the row, but assures him that her school will be large enough in the fall; shares news of acquaintances in Mobile; hopes that he has recovered from his fractured rib; asks why he cannot obtain labor on shares, which seems the most widely used method of obtaining labor; is seeking employment for George and asks if the apothecary's or some other business would be preferred; chastises George through him [JRC] for not writing and explains that while she teaches school and takes in sewing in addition to her and Carter's needs, she still has time to write her grandson; informs him that Carter is again serving on a steamer, this one the General Rodgers; will send him $25 on the first of June and reminds him to send for it.
  - [John R. Coupland], Willoughby, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 17 Aug[ust] 1866., 4 pages. ALS. Incomplete. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Has worked hard all summer in the fields and is proud of the work he has done; had told the children that once the corn crop was in they would have pones and griddle-cakes and hominy and mush, and all were looking forward to October; describes the drought that grips Eastern Virginia and fears all his crop will be scorched by the sun; despairs for his family as he is too poor to do his duty to them properly; explains that he wish the $25 she sent to him had been sent later as it was already spent by the time the sheriff came to collect taxes on the farm; was able to pay the taxes by John Morrison's kindness, where otherwise his furniture would have been impounded; informs her that George will work in the engineer corps for the railroad for $60 per month until she can secure him a better job in the mercantile line.
  - Carter [Coupland], on board Steamer Prairie State, Montgomery, [Alabama], to Juliana Dorsey, Mobile, Alabama, 28 Nov[ember] 1866., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Writes her faithfully every week and wonders if she receives his letters; worries that she is not well or in need because she does not write; wishes that he could provide for her and make her comfortable, but he hasn't the means; informs her that "Every thing looks gloomy" as the merchants are broke or soon will be because there is no money or business in that part of the county; is not sure when the steamer will be sold, either this term or the next.
  - Leonora Coupland, Williamsburg, [Virginia], to grandmother [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 13 April [1863?]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Describes the first raid when the Confederate men came by their home and she offered them water; mentions that during the second raid the Confederates drove the enemy out of town; informs her that Cousin Hattie has gone to Richmond and that Cousin Mattie has gone away; was forced to take shelter at the hospital to avoid the cannonballs.
  - J[uliana] D[orsey], Williamsburg, [Virginia] to Carter [Coupland], n.p., 31 Dec[embe]r n.y., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Informs him that Mr. Ritchie died about a fortnight previous after a long illness resulting from his injury; shares news of the family visiting her in Williamsburg; mourns Mrs. Blair's losses, for "that is human agony to see one's children, one after another, fill an early grave"; is glad that he is tired of hotel life and will join a family's fireside; asks him to raise $1180 for her if she can do without it; informs that John [R. Coupland] is at Story Point and cannot get back due to the weather.
  - [Juliana Dorsey], Greensboro, to Sue [H. Coupland], n.p., 16 April [186?]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Worries for them because she has had no letters from them; hopes she can get an efficient cook and someone to help her; gives advice regarding the children; is sorry they had had another raid; hopes she can secure enough provisions for her family; shares that Tiff was able to get her $100 cow home after they had lost a more elegant cow, and had been living without milk and butter; will leave for Mobile the following Tuesday and will stay with Mollie [Marshall] for the summer; has recovered from her "Yankee consumption" and hopes that she [SHC] will get over her troubles.
    Including ALS from [Juliana Dorsey] to John [R. Coupland]. Hopes that he can send a wagonload up now as things are selling quite high in Richmond; suggests that Mr. Spear may thereafter be able to make regular trips; mentions that if they could get up the corn and oats they could get government prices for them, and several hundred dollars could be made. 1 p.
  - [Juliana Dorsey], Mobile, [Alabama], to John [R. Coupland], n.p., 6 May [1863?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Has improved greatly since she went up to Tiff's; informs him that Carter had had diphtheria while she was gone but is recovered; wonders what Julia means when she says that he is a conscript, whether he has been conscripted or whether he is only subject to it; asks how he is "getting on, in the domestic way" and whether he has a servant; feels safe in Mobile for although the Yankees are threatening by land, the city leaders have been drilling the citizens for a year on home defense; will go to stay with Mollie [Marshall] and informs him that John [Marshall] is stationed at Pascagoula.
  - Wm. H. Sheild, to Jno. [John] R. Coupland, W[illia]msburg, [Virginia], n.d., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Informs him that the generous county of James City has provided York County with a judge, a clerk, a commonwealth's attorney, and a superintendent of schools; asks him to combat an electioneering dodge to be used against him; describes the election in which he is running.
  Series 2: Accounts
- Accounts, 1850-1866., 232 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Accounts of Carter Coupland, 1850-1860., 83 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Accounts of John R. Coupland, 1858-1866., 21 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Accounts of Juliana Dorsey, 1851-1863, 122 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Accounts of other persons. 1862., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Unidentified accounts. 1857-1863., 4 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  Series 3: Miscellaneous Items
- Miscellaneous Items. (Box-folder 2:6-7)
  - Statement made by Juliana Dorsey, 13 November 1851., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:6)
    Statement made by Juliana Dorsey, regarding her slaves and household furniture loaned by her to her son John R. Coupland.
  - Prayers, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:6)
    Prayers written by Juliana Dorsey for her sons, John R. Coupland and Carter Coupland.
  - Visiting cards, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
    Two visiting cards in an envelope addressed to Mrs. Juliana Dorsey.
  - Will extracts, 1876., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
    Two extracts from the will of Juliana Dorsey.
  - Cards written to Miss Mattie Pierce, 1856, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
    Five cards written to Miss Mattie Pierce regarding social engagements in Williamsburg.
  - Invitation, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:6)
    Invitation to Miss Mattie Pierce to attend the annual encampment, Mobile Rifles.
  - Subscription list, 1860., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:6)